# 大家好 現在今天下了點小雨呦
Hi everyone! There's a few drops of rain today.
# 叫老公去砍竹子他不願意砍
I asked my younger brother to chop some bamboo but he's quite reluctant.
# 我去砍一點竹子 順便看下有沒有冬笋啊
So I'm going instead. I'll also see if there are any winter bamboo shoots on the way.
# 去挖點冬笋下來
I'll get some if I see any.
# 就從這裡上去 那條路被我堵住啦
We're getting up form this side. I've blocked the path over there.
# 那小豬老是從那裡跑出來
The piglets are always getting away from that side.
# 這裡要搞個坑來好站腳
Let me make a pit here, for us to step on.
# 這裡上去
This way.
# 這可以站一下啦
We can step on the pit.
# 這條路很近的
This route is much shorter.
# 五十米都不到 就到竹林啦
It's not even fifty metres to the bamboo forest.
# 我們廠後面這片竹林啊 被我們包下來啦
We have taken this bamboo forest, which is right behind our site.
# 以後砍竹子就不用那麼 那麼麻煩啦
It saves us so much, so much trouble getting the bamboo hereafter.
# 去那麼遠的地方砍
We don't need to go far far away anymore.
# 以前都要跑
We needed to walk,
# 幾公里 然後要 還要上山上去砍
a few kilometres. And then we needed, still needed to go onto the hill.
# 很遠的 可能走山路都要走
It's really far away. It's like thirty minutes to an hour,
# 走半個小時到一個小時
just to walk up the hill.
# 現在也很方便啦 現在離
It's much more convenient now. It's like,
# 我們那個竹鼠棚啊 只有五十米都不到
not even fifty metres, from our shed of the bamboo rats.
# 看[SIC]下來就把它弄下去就好
We can simply chop it down, and bring it down. That's it!
# 要過那邊去砍
We need to go to that side.
# 誒呦小狗 小來啦
Ayo, doggy! You're coming with us?
# 從這裡
This way.
# 這個擋住了
It's blocking me.
# 擋住了我就把這全部砍掉
I'm chopping down everything which blocks my way.
# 這樣也會擋
It's still blocking.
# 這棵把它 這棵我都砍掉
And this one, I'll chop this one too.
# 這個是死的
It's dead.
# 這乾了這個竹子 我們也把它砍掉
This bamboo is dried. We're chopping it down as well.
# 這沒用的
It's useless.
# 這也砍掉
This one too,
# 在這一大堆
the whole lot here,
# 扎堆的
all of them.
# 葉子都沒有
There's not even a leaf.
# 這老竹子
An old bamboo.
# 這幾根夠一餐啦
These several bamboos here are enough for a meal.
# 我把它砍下來 一段一段 把它背回去
Let me chop them into chunks, and carry them back.
# 這個是
This is,
# 壞的
rotten.
# 這種竹子太老啦
These bamboos are far too old.
# 如果我們不砍掉的話也會死掉的
They would just die even if we did not chop them down.
# 這種 像這個
It's er, it's like,
# 年都會長出來 那個嫩的
the new bamboos are growing every year, I mean the young ones.
# 就是等於說
I mean,
# 春戻啊 那麼大春笋
the spring bamboo shoots, which are that big,
# 一年就把它可以長到那麼大的竹子
can be a bamboo tree of this size in just a year.
# 所以這個要 適當的要砍一點
So it needs to be chopped down a bit.
# 不砍的話這個竹子很丑的
Otherwise the new bamboos would be very ugly.
# 等下我們把這個
We will need to,
# 不漂亮的把它砍掉
chop away those which are not pretty,
# 把漂亮的留下來
leaving only the pretty ones.
# 一年 幾年過後 這個竹林就很漂亮的
The bamboo forest would be very pretty after a year, a couple of years.
# 全是大竹子
All are big bamboos,
# 大毛竹
big moso bamboos.
# 這個尾巴就不要啦
The tail needs to be chopped away.
# 這尾巴很利的哦
The tail is really sharp.
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 出水了
The fluid is coming out.
# 這竹子都爛了
This bamboo is already rotten.
# 爛的
Rotten
# 爛的我要背回去 用來
I don't care. I'll take it back, as
# 用來燒火
as firewoods,
# 用來烤竹鼠
for grilling bamboo rats.
# 你看 小狗都上來了
Look! The doggy is also coming up.
# 小狗 這條小黑
Doggy. This is Blacky.
# 懷孕了哦 小黑
She's pregnant, Blacky.
# 這都懷孕了
She's pregnant too.
# 那麼小都懷孕了
She's pregnant though she's still a kid.
# 唉 走開走開走開走開
Ay! Go 'way, go 'way, go 'way, go 'way!
# 我要幹活
I'm working!
# 等我下幹活的時候陪你們玩
I'll play with you when I'm not working.
# 讓開讓開讓開讓開
Go, go, go, go!
# 甚麼意思
What does it mean?
# 叫它們走它們都不走
They're not leaving even if ask them to.
# 把它捆起來
Let me tie them up.
# 好 我先挖幾個笋子
Alright! I'll get some bamboo shoots.
# 看有沒有竹笋
Let's see if there are any.
# 這刀放這裡
I leave the knife here.
# 今天太旱啦
It's too dry this year.
# 都沒有 都沒看到竹笋
No, I can't see any bamboo shoots.
# 沒下雨 所以那個 竹笋很少
There's no rain. So, I mean, there are hardly any bamboo shoots.
# 下次我要抱一條小豬上來
I should come with a piglet next time.
# 讓它來拱
Let it dig.
# 因為野豬它也可以異得到那個竹笋的
Cuz the wild boars know where to dig out the bamboo shoots.
# 那小豬應該也能拱得到
So I think the piglets can do it too.
# 拿 拿個繩子來 把 把它栓起來
I'll take, take a piece of rope, as, as a leash.
# 別一個都找不到 那麼慘的
Give me at least one! Getting back home empty-handed is too miserable.
# 看 這裡有一棵樹
Look! Here's a tree.
# 你看這個樹桩上 長了一棵樹出來哦
Look! A tree is growing from this dead wood.
# 很厲害哦
Marvelous!
# 很漂亮吧
Isn't it pretty?
# 今年笋子好難挖呀
It's really hard to get the bamboo shoots this year.
# 挖了差不多快兩個小時了
I've been digging for almost two hours.
# 一個都沒找到
But I can't find even one.
# 要不要這樣子啊
Is it really that bad?
# 有一個哦
Here's one!
# 今年挖了第一個冬笋
It's our first bamboo shoot this winter.
# 哎呀 越搞越大了
Aya! It's getting bigger.
# 今年
This year,
# 搞塊臘肉來炒
let's fry it with some cure pork.
# 夠大 夠大 夠大 夠大
Big enough, big enough, big enough, big enough!
# 就沒有啦 就一個
And no more, just one.
# 還可以呦
It's not too bad.
# 這個今算年蠻大的啦
It's already a rather large one this year.
# 是啊
Yup!
# 今天晚上我要用來炒臘肉
I'll fry it with the cured pork tonight.
# 那個小豬 小豬肉來的
The piglets, the pork is from the piglets.
# 味道很不錯的哦
It tastes really nice.
# 誒
Eh?
# 又一個
One more!
# 耶 這個好小哦
Ye! It's so small.
# 哎呀 也不小哦
Aya! No, it's not that small.
# 不要嫌棄大家小
I shouldn't judge it my its size.
# 感覺它裡面肉好吃
It seems to me that it's quite tasty.
# 你看 這麼小 這個
Look! It's so small, this one.
# 今年的竹笋就那麼大一點 不大
The bamboo shoots this year are all that tiny, not so big.
# 去看一下有 還有沒有
Let's go on and see any, if there are any more.
# 哎
Ay!
# 又一個哦
One more here!
# 啊 這個大一點
Ah! This one is a bit bigger.
# 哇
Wa!
# 這個不剛才那個還大
It's not, the one just now is even bigger.
# 哎呀 這個
Aya! It's,
# 可以喲 這個
it's not bad.
# 不大不小 剛剛好
Not too big, not too small. Perfect!
# 放在這裡先
Leave it here first.
# 看一下還有沒有
Let's see if there are any more.
# 沒啦
No more
# 這邊沒有啦
No more here
# 找不到
Can't see any
# 你看 小黑 趴在那裡
Look at Blacky! She's lying there,
# 喘氣
panting.
# 它也很累啦
She's also very tired.
# 你看 誒呀 小黑
Look! Eya! Blacky!
# 這兩隻狗
These two dogs,
# 它們 很肥啦 它們 有點胖
they're very fat now. They're a bit chubby.
# 多爬一下山 多鍛煉一下身體
Hike more! Train up your body!
# 就像我這樣
Just like me.
# 知不知道
Do you get it?
# 它老是想 它想親我
It always wants, it wants to kiss me.
# 誒呀
Eya!
# 你看 小黑
Look! Blacky!
# 小黑比較乖啦 現在
Blacky is a good girl now.
# 看它牙齒
Look at her teeth.
# 我去哪裡 它們就跟著我去哪裡
They're following me, wherever I go.
# 好乖呀
Good girl!
# 呵呵
Hm hm.
# 呵呵呵
Hm hm hm.
# 這個也是 這個是攝影小哥最喜歡的這條狗
And this dog too. This is Mr. Cameraman's most favourite dog.
# 它現在 它現在老是 老是喜歡黏著我啦
He now, he now always, always likes clinging on me.
# 你看 哎呀 你想幹嘛
Look! Aya! What do you want?
# 不能跟你們玩啦 我要幹活啦
It's the end of the game time. I need to get back to my work.
# 等一下今天晚上沒 沒菜吃
Otherwise we have noth, nothing for dinner tonight.
# 再找一下
Find again!
# 你看 挖了一下午
Look! We spent the whole afternoon,
# 就挖了這4個
only to have these four,
# 還一個那麼小的
including this tiny little one.
# 那麼小的我也把它檢回去 炒啦
I don't care. I'll take it back, and have it fried.
# 還有一個
One more here.
# 就這4個
So just four.
# 挖啦 太累啦
It's really a tiring work.
# 不挖啦 回去摘快臘肉來
Enough! Let's get back and fetch some cured pork,
# 炒一炒
and fry.
# 喝口水來
Let me get a sip.
# 很口渴啦
I'm really thirsty.
# 啊
Ah!
# 先搞下這個竹笋 這個竹笋要把它
Let's process the bamboo shoots first. The ends of the bamboo shoots
# 砍掉一節的
need to be chopped off.
# 然後再
And then,
# 划一下
slice it here.
# 划一下的話 就是可以這樣子
It's because it can be,
# 直接掰開它
cracked open right away.
# 就搞了那麼一丟丟啦
Then it becomes just a tiny little bit now.
# 它的肉就剩那 剩下那麼一丁點啦
The edible part is just the tiny little bit remaining.
# 這個也是啊
The same for this one.
# 這個竹笋 現在十幾塊錢一斤啊
The bamboo shoots, now cost more than 10 RMB a pound.
# 這麼小的
Though it's small,
# 也是我辛苦挖回來的
I earn it through my hard work.
# 這個冬笋
The winter bamboo shoots,
# 我們不挖掉也會壞掉的
would be rotten anyway, even if they're left there.
# 所以要通通挖掉
So we need to take them all.
# 然後我們切好
After cutting it into pieces,
# 然後再來切臘肉
we can move on to the cured pork.
# 把它切成一片片的 誒
Cut it into slices, eh?
# 這個刀 這個刀怎麼中間凹進去的
Why is there, why is there a pit in the middle of the knife?
# 一次換一把刀來
I'll take another knife next time.
# 就那麼一丁點
Just a tiny little bit
# 這個
Well,
# 冬笋 要用那個
the bamboo shoots, need to be,
# 煮開 過一下水呀
boiled, boiled in the water.
# 不然的話 它會有點那個
Otherwise, it would be a bit, I mean,
# 怎麼說呢 就是 吃了喉嚨不舒服那種
it's like, well, your throat might feel a bit funny.
# 放水煮一下
Boil it in the water.
# 先把這兩塊臘肉放進去煮一下
Let me boil these two piece of cured pork for a while first.
# 這個
It's er...
# 現在可以啦
it's alright now.
# 這個竹笋
The bamboo shoots,
# 要過一下水
need to be boiled in the water.
# 把這個
And er...
# 誒呀
Eya!
# 還想跑
You wanna run away?
# 先把這個
First,
# 搞一下
get it done.
# 好香啊
It smells great!
# 先把這個
First, here,
# 這個
here,
# 上次沒刮幹淨
It wasn't thoroughly cleaned last time.
# 就先
So I,
# 猛刮一下
scratch and scratch and scratch!
# 這個皮
The skin,
# 看上去還上次沒 沒搞乾淨
it doesn't seem to have been thoroughly cleaned last time.
# 這次拿來餵狗
Let me give it to the dogs this time.
# 小黑
Blacky!
# 誒呀 你嫌棄呀 等下都沒得吃哦
Aya! You don't like it? Take it or you won't get any.
# 把它切成一片片的
Cut it into slices.
# 哇 這個切得夠漂亮
Wa! They look so pretty now,
# 夠細的哦
small and thin.
# 以我們是直接用刀來剁
I used to be simply chopping it by a knife.
# 剛剛我不是給你吃了一塊嗎 還想要
What do you want? Haven't I just given you a piece?
# 可以啦 你看
Alright! Look!
# 等一下 要淌乾淨來
Wait! Clean the plate first.
# 哇 好香啊
Wa! It smells really good!
# 這個剛挖回來新鮮的竹笋
These are our freshly picked bamboo shoots.
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 有種那個 淡淡香味
It's like, a subtle fragrance,
# 竹子的香味
a note of bamboo,
# 跟竹鼠的香味融入在起 (註︰怎麼又竹鼠了？)
together with the aroma of bamboo rats.
# 那種 那種味道
A fine combination of everything.
# 簡直就是
It's really,
# 不會形容
no words can describe.
# 不會形容那種味道
It's not a taste that I can describe by words.
# 好香哦
Wonderful!
# 先把這個豬肉 炒一下
Let me fry the pork first.
# 然後把這個
And then,
# 放竹笋下去
together with the bamboo shoots.
# 這個不用放鹽了的
We don't need any salt this time.
# 這個臘肉上那麼多鹽
There's already plenty of salt on the cured pork.
# 你看 這個 (註︰以下數句是碎碎念，他應該也不知道自己想說說甚麼)
Look!
# 竹笋
The bamboo shoots,
# 金黃色的
are golden brown.
# 跟那個腦肉
Together with the cured pork,
# 香豬肉
form the Huanjiang pigs,
# 混合在一起
they're combined,
# 攪伴在一起
to a dish.
# 加點
Put some...
# 是老抽
It's dark soy sauce.
# 要生抽
I need light soy sauce.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 起鍋
Done!
# 哇
Wa!
# 一
An
# 一個香噴噴的
An aromatic dish of
# 竹笋炒臘肉
bamboo shoots fried with cured pork,
# 就出來啦 (註︰這些王剛式的結尾大家想想麼搞吧)
is done.
# 看上去都有食欲
It looks really appetizing.
# 我去嘗一下
Let me try.
# 嘗一下這個竹笋 看味道怎麼樣
Let me try the bamboo shoots and see how it tastes.
# 嗯
Um!
# 好嫩啊
Tender and juicy!
# 一咬就裂開
I don't need to chew hard.
# 可以呦 這個竹笋
It's not bad, the bamboo shoots.
# 它們甘甜甘甜的
It's savory sweet.
# 吃塊豬肉
Have a piece of pork.
# 這個豬是我自己養的
It's my own pig.
# 嗯 還可以喲
Um! It's not too bad.
# 好香啊
It smells really great.
# 嗯
Um!
# 你看 那小狗
Look! That puppy,
# 想出來
it wants to come out.
# 它都以為 (註︰怎麼以為？不是真的嗎？)
It thinks that,
# 我有甚麼好吃的
I had some good food for it.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 今天的視頻就到這裡的
The video ends here.
# 準備吃晚飯啦
We need to get ready for dinner.